<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A true discourse of an ouerthrow giuen to the armie of the Leaguers in Prouince by Messieurs D'Esdiguieres and Lauallette. Translated verbatim out of the French copie, printed at Tours by Iamet Mettayer.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1591</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 11 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 4 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A01177</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 11290</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S116494</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99851710</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99851710</idno>
            <idno type="VID">17001</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A01177)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 17001)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1306:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A true discourse of an ouerthrow giuen to the armie of the Leaguers in Prouince by Messieurs D'Esdiguieres and Lauallette. Translated verbatim out of the French copie, printed at Tours by Iamet Mettayer.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Thomas Purfoot, dwelling in Saint Nicholas shambles within the New-rents,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1591]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Publication date from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Peterborough Cathedral. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Lesdiguiéres, François de Bonne, --  duc de, 1543-1626.</term>
               <term>Holy League, 1576-1593 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>France --  History --  Wars of the Huguenots, 1562-1598 --  Sources --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:17001:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17001:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A TR<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>E DISCO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RSE OF an ouerthrow giuen to the armie of the</hi> Leaguers in Prouince: By Meſsieurs D' Eſdiguieres and Lauallette. ¶ Tranſlated verbatim out of the French Copie, Printed at Tours by Iamet Mettayer.</p>
            <p>LONDON, <hi>Printed by Thomas Purfoot, dwelling in</hi> Saint Nicholas ſhambles within the New-rents.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb facs="tcp:17001:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17001:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A true diſcourſe of an ouerthrow giuen to the</hi> armie of the Leaguers in Prouince, vpon Monday in Eaſter vveeke, being the 15 day of Aprill laſt paſt. 1591.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>Vr gratious God ſeemeth to ſleepe for a ſeaſon and to be careleſſe of his choſen people, that he may bee glorified in his woonderfull workes, by bringing them which truſt to much in humain ſtrength into the conſideration of his vnſpeakeable power, who taketh pleaſure in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtrength of men, but ſcattereth the great hoſts and ſquadrons of ſuch as arme themſelues contrarie to his will, euen as chaffe before the winde, and in the twinckling of an eye (as it were) dooth ſo abate their pride, that by the hand of a few of his people he bringeth them to nought, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king them equall with the duſt, and leauing them as a preie to be deuoured of woolues, and ſuch lyke rauenous beaſts.</p>
            <p>The enemies had great confidence in the King of <hi>Spaine</hi> (now called out of this worlde to render an account before the ſoueraign Monarch, of the manifold extorſions and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious cruelties committed by him) who aſſured the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues that he would ſend ſo many men of warre into all partes of Fraunce (as he hath done, though in vaine) that in ſhorte time he might vanquiſh and ſubdue the king and gaine his Crowne. For the ſame cauſe, vpon the death of this Arch-tyrant king, the duke of <hi>Sauoy</hi> is gone into <hi>Spaine,</hi> and hath giuen ouer the enterpriſe he purpoſed againſt the towne of <hi>Marſeilles,</hi> which by ſundrie waies and meanes he had prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed
<pb facs="tcp:17001:3"/> with diuers of the inhabitants who receiued into their town ſome ſtore of corne, cauſing ſuch men as they ſuſpected and would not be conformable to their wils, to forſake the town, which things they had done by ſo much the more wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly as they ſuffered the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſlip eaſilie into the nets of their rebellion, ſome of their owne accord, ſome others by y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> helpe and aſſiſtance of a puiſſant armie of the Spaniards, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoiens, and Prouincials which marched within the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey vnder the conduct of the <hi>Count Martine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ga,</hi> of <hi>Monſieur de Vitelli</hi> Colonel of the duke of <hi>Sauoies</hi> horſemen leaguers, and of <hi>Monſ. S. Romani</hi> general of the footmen who know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that <hi>Meſsieurs D'Eſdiguieres</hi> and <hi>Lauallette,</hi> were ioined on that ſide which <hi>Riez</hi> lieth on, and that <hi>Monſ. Lauallette</hi> was departed for the ſame intent from <hi>Ciſteron</hi> the 13 daye of Aprill, hauing cauſed certaine peeces of ordinaunce to bee brought with their troopes, and ſeing likewiſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they might greatly hinder their enterpriſes, reſolued to approach neare vnto them, not ſo much to prouoke them to a battle, in that they were foure to one, as thinking to keepe them at a baye, and ſo cauſe them to retire. But they could not bee ignorant hauing had ſo great proofe of the wiſe conduct, ſingular watchfulnes, and proſperous ſucceſſe of this valiant Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain <hi>Monſ. D'Eſdiguieres,</hi> who being aided by the venterous champion <hi>Seigneur Lauallette,</hi> and armed with a iuſt cauſe in defence of their king and ſtate, not fearing the great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the enemies, whome with courage and reſolution he valiauntly charged ſo oft as there was occaſion, as maye more euidently appeare by this diſcourſe enſuing.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sparron</hi> is a village and a caſtell in <hi>Prouince,</hi> about fyue leagues from <hi>Aix,</hi> the Lord whereof in times paſt held him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe newter, taking neither partie: neuertheleſſe hee enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned in his Caſtell the Lord gouernour of the partie roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all and his troupe. A great number of the Sauoien horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men
<pb facs="tcp:17001:3"/> went to lodge in the ſame village of <hi>Sparron.</hi> Now <hi>Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieurs D'Eſdiguieres</hi> and <hi>Lauallette</hi> receiuing aduertiſement of the enemies being there, without delay they marched thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther alſo with their forces, and on monday in Eaſter weke being the 15 of the ſame moneth did aſſaile them with ſuch fury and reſolution that in a ſhort ſpace recouering the beſt aduantage, they gaue them an vtter ouerthrow: they tooke 15 Enſigns, foure Cornets from the horſemen, 500 horſes whoſe owners lay dead in the place, &amp; aboue 250 gentlemen wel mounted were caried away priſoners by a compoſition made at the ſame time in the village. The <hi>Seigneur</hi> of <hi>Vitelly,</hi> collonell of the duke of Sauoies horſemen leaguers, and <hi>Monſ. S. Romani,</hi> generall of the enemies footmen did yeelde themſelues priſoners alſo. The Frenchmen of <hi>Prouince</hi> wer ſent home to their houſes by the ſaid Lordes <hi>D' Eſdiguieres</hi> &amp; <hi>Lauallette</hi> with each one a white ſtick in his hand. More then 500 Sauoiens were ſent to <hi>Tollon</hi> to <hi>Monſ. Lauallette</hi> his gallies, therein requiting the duke of <hi>Sauoy</hi> with ſuch mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure as he had meated vnto ſome of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kings troups before. The moſt part of the forts &amp; ſtrong holds of <hi>Prouince,</hi> wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the rebels had commaundement, hearing of ſo great an ouerthrow to be giuen their ſide, are reduced &amp; brought vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the kings obedience excepting only the citie of <hi>Aix</hi> which y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid Lords haue with al diligence enuironed &amp; blocked in</p>
            <p>The <hi>Count Martinenga</hi> who had the leading of 800 Horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men perceiuing that there was nothing to be gayned but blowes, &amp; that the ſaid Lords &amp; their troups ſpared not to lay on loade, reſolued therefore to truſt to their legges and to ſaue themſelues by flight with 300 horſe which were al y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> could eſcape from that encounter: the reſt were all either ſlayne or taken: &amp; our ſouldiers &amp; men of war, beſides ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny riche priſoners, got in this conflicte about 350. horſſes of ſeruice, there were alſo thirtye Captaynes taken beſides the two commaunders. <hi>Monſ. Lauallette</hi> hath armed two galleys at <hi>Tollon:</hi> &amp; theſe two noble Lords proſecuting their notable victory haue wonne y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> towns of <hi>Digne</hi> and <hi>Lines,</hi> and it is ſaid that <hi>Mouglon</hi> is now in parle to render vnto the king and to ſhake off the rebellious yoke.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:17001:4"/>
            <p>Thus we ſee that humaine forces withſtanding the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunces of God, are in a moment ouerwhelmed.</p>
            <p>The King of <hi>Spaine</hi> is dead, who was the greateſt ſuppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the league, &amp; the rebellion in Fraunce. The Leaguers haue loſt a puiſſant armie of Spaniards, Sauoiens, and other ſtrangers in <hi>Prouince,</hi> which is now God be thanked almoſt all ſubdued. <hi>Italy</hi> is diſburdened ſundrye waies, by the death of this tyrant. The King on the other ſide is proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent in his affaires, which the Lord doth daily proſper with his heauenly bleſſing. Moreouer there are two regiments of <hi>VVallons</hi> defeated in <hi>Picardy.</hi> God exerciſeth his iuſtice more and more vpon his enimies, ſeeing that the clemencie of the Prince whome hee hath giuen vnto vs ſerueth to no purpoſe to bring them to reaſon, and that now at this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant they are ſo ſtubborne, that vnder the Duke of <hi>Maines</hi> authoritie, they will at a certaine day of the moneth haue a conuention of all their partiſans rebels in the town of <hi>Reins</hi> there to hold an aſſembly of eſtates to conſult of the affairs of the league, which are in a pittifull taking vpon the vnex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected death of the king of <hi>Spaine,</hi> which is ſo preiudiciall to their rebellious faction.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mounſieur de Nemours</hi> to counterpoiſe a matter ſo wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of regard by the rebels in <hi>Prouince,</hi> &amp; thinking to mende vp that which was ſo torne on their ſide, being at <hi>Lions</hi> a little after this ouerthrow giuen, ſent into <hi>Daulphine</hi> three or foure hundred horſſe, carrieng with them good ſtore of ladders and Petarts, and hauing paſſed the <hi>Liſer</hi> towards <hi>la Roche,</hi> and leauing their horſſes on this ſide, marched a league on foot being armed, and would haue planted their ladders, and giuen a ſkalado to <hi>Valence,</hi> but they came not within muſquet ſhot thereof: for returning in haſt beeing purſued, they left 37 ladders in a barne, within a quarter of a league of <hi>Valence.</hi> They had ſo ill ſurceſſe through their
<pb facs="tcp:17001:4"/> long retreat that they loſt 80 or 100 of their horſes, wherof ſome were woorth 800 crownes, and yet were conſtrained to returne againe without doing any ſeruice.</p>
            <p>The Leaguers being but a few which could eſcape at the ouer throw of <hi>Sparron</hi> haue ſente to ſeeke their maiſter the duke of <hi>Sauoy</hi> in <hi>Spaine,</hi> and are in great perplexitie becauſe they heare no newes of his Excellencie. He hath loſt more by his departure than he ſhall gaine at his returne.</p>
            <p>We are to giue God thanks for ſo many bleſſings wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with it pleaſeth him to endue the King and his affairs to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comfort in the end his good ſubiects ſo much oppreſſed, and almoſt burnt as it were with the fire of ciuill wars, kindled by the rebels, who go about to continue it: howbeit the king of compaſſion vpon the poore &amp; miſerable eſtate of his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects, more than of deſire to eſtabliſh himſelfe in that which appertaineth vnto him, doth enforce himſelfe by all meanes and chiefly by his mildneſſe, mercifulneſſe and clemencie towardes the vanquiſhed rebels, to quenche and put out wholy this fire which they ſought to entertaine, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by his people and commonwealth might floriſh in an vniuerſall peace.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
